We got into this thing with the best
intentions, really. I never int-
Oh, I'm sorry. Did I break your
concentration?
What drives our emotional reaction to
the violence we see in films?
[screaming]
The [__] are we doing? Because it's not
just about seeing it. We need to feel
the violence we see, right?
>> [screaming]
>> It needs to serve a purpose in the story
we're being immersed in. Otherwise, we
lose any narrative substance,
and it just becomes spectacle.
For spectacle's sake.
Which isn't always a bad thing. It's
just a branch of cinema where the
filmmakers are going for a cinematic
experience [music] that is more visual
and action-driven.
>> [screaming]
>> So, if you want to study a film that
really makes you feel the brutal,
moral,
and destructive weight of the very brief
moments of violence within its story,
then look no further than Denis
Villeneuve's Sicario.
Are you okay?
Yeah.
And it has a lot to do with how
Sicario's violence was pieced together
by Denis Villeneuve, who visualized it,
Roger Deakins, who shot it, and Joe
Walker, who edited it. And the editing
is what I want to talk about today,
because in this case, our emotional
reactions to the violence we see [music]
in Sicario are largely due to how Joe
Walker presents it to us. And that's
because of a thing called continuity of
emotion.
If you ask any great editor, emotion is
often considered to be the most
important factor when making cuts.
Because emotion is how you get an
audience of inherently emotional
creatures, aka us humans, to invest in
stories. So, maintaining continuity of
emotion when cutting is generally
considered [music] to be the mark of a
really good editor. And one of the
things that's so good about Joe Walker's
editing, not just in Sicario, but across
his entire outstanding body of work, is
how well he manages to maintain
emotional continuity in his
storytelling, even when things get
incredibly violent.
You tiny thing. Which is no easy task,
because these are the moments where a
story's core emotions can sometimes fall
to the wayside in favor [music] of
spectacle. Pulling this off is the mark
of an editor who truly understands the
characters and emotions at the core of a
film's story, and how to convey them
effectively. So, let's take a closer
look at how Walker manages to maintain
such strong emotional continuity when
cutting together the violence of
Sicario, despite [music] a surprisingly
big and noteworthy shift to the rhythm
of his cuts towards the end of the film.
Sicario's story can be split quite
cleanly into two [music] parts. The
first part, in which we the audience
inhabit Kate Macer's perspective, and
the second part, in which we take on
Alejandro Gillick's perspective.
When we're in Kate's perspective, the
violence feels [music] visceral and
VISUALLY DISRUPTIVE.
AND THAT'S QUITE SIMPLY BECAUSE IT NEEDS
TO reflect her state of being
uninitiated, I just want to know what
I'm getting into. unsettled,
Jesus Christ.
and completely discombobulated. And we
need to feel [music] that as the
audience. When there are gunshots, the
cuts are rapid and disorientating, often
splicing together multiple camera angles
in extremely quick succession.
To make it a bit more obvious, let's
take a closer look at how Walker cuts
together the gunshots during the border
crossing sequence.
It's worth noting that this sequence,
like most of Sicario, was storyboarded.
So, Deakins and Villeneuve knew
precisely what they were shooting, and
they didn't really go beyond what they
needed. Now, even though a sequence may
be storyboarded, it isn't a cheat sheet
that tells an editor exactly when to
make a cut. But it probably would have
meant that Walker had quite a clear idea
of what this sequence should look like
when he constructed it in the edit. And
that's only a good thing, because it
will have given him a lot more clarity
in knowing when to dial up the tension
by stretching out the key moments of
build-up,
and when to release it so effectively in
the few shockingly abrupt moments of
violence we are given. For instance,
when the shooting starts with the red
and parlor, there are six camera setups
that make room for Walker's eight rapid
cuts.
The [__] are we doing?
For the green civic, there are also six
camera setups, this time between seven
cuts.
And for the attempt on Kate in the SUV,
there are five different setups between
all seven cuts.
[__] That's a lot of coverage for each
of these moments, which by themselves
are actually very short injections of
violence in the grander scheme of the
entire 4 and 1/2 minute sequence,
collectively taking up only 14 seconds
of screen time. Walker's approach to
cutting achieves a couple of notable
things here. A, it keeps the violence
grounded as part of the story, and B, it
makes the whole sequence really
unsettling.
Jesus Christ.
And the key to this seems to be how he
uses reaction shots. It'll be safer in
America. No, it won't. Notice how we cut
to Kate's reaction just as the first
bout of shooting starts.
And then again cut to her follow-up
reaction when it stops.
The [__] are we doing?
If we were to remove these shots of
Kate, a couple of key things would
happen. Firstly, the purpose of the
violence within the narrative would be
lost, because as the audience, we
wouldn't understand quite how illegal
this [music] entire sequence is. We
would just have two cold, brutal moments
of men being executed without much
narrative context. These cuts to Kate,
specifically this one, the [__] are we
doing? Gives the violence its moral
weight in the story.
Secondly, without seeing Kate reacting,
these segments would lose their
viscerality significantly. It would
become violence for the sake of
violence, action without character. And
we simply wouldn't feel the emotions
that Villeneuve wanted us to feel at
this point in the story, namely the same
stress and panic that Kate is feeling.
Not to mention, jumping around from the
shooting to the back of the SUV [music]
with Kate so rapidly really nicely
achieves the goal of making this all
feel a lot more disorientating. So, now
let's compare this with Walker's cutting
during Alejandro's brutally vengeful
killing [music] spree in the film's
final act.
If we were to describe the state of
Kate's character throughout the story of
Sicario, we'd be forced to use words
like uninitiated, Get this service
weapon out.
unsettled, Kate.
What is it?
discombobulated. [music]
Whereas for Alejandro, we'd be looking
for words like surgical,
>> [music]
>> unflinching,
dispassionate.
And that's the picture Denis Villeneuve
and Roger Deakins paint when looking at
how they filmed the violence here. And
more importantly, [music] it's the
picture Joe Walker paints with how he
cuts it together.
Where violence from Kate's perspective
is wildly disorientating and fast-paced,
when we experience the violence from
Alejandro's perspective, the cutting is
much more restrained. There are cuts,
but there are far fewer of them. And
more importantly, there is much less
camera coverage of the violence. At
most, we cut between two camera angles,
and at the least, we get no cuts and
hold on a single angle. It's surgical,
like Alejandro.
For example, this moment, [music] which
could easily have been filmed and edited
with a similar degree of disorientation
to the border crossing, features only
one cut.
For the record, this all highlights not
just how much Deakins' cinematographic
choices nailed the brief and captured
the characters so well, [music]
but how well all the different technical
aspects of Sicario gelled together to
deliver [music] the story, too. A point
further emphasized by the fact that the
next time Alejandro fires his gun, we
get zero cuts, as Deakins uses a more
dynamic composition in the form of a
tracking shot, which keeps [music] us
moving in tandem with the now
unstoppable force that is Alejandro.
Notice then how the camera intentionally
[music]
pans downwards here, briefly
spotlighting Alejandro's kill. Given
that the aim at this point in the story
is to gradually reveal to to audience
just how ruthless and violent Alejandro
really is. This is [music] a great
example of the subtle creative touches
that really bring out the [music]
immorality at the core of the story.
And then we have the final, and perhaps
most memorable, moments in which [music]
a weapon is fired in the film.
A moment of violence so shocking that it
makes a cartel executioner react like
this.
And similar to Kate's reactions in the
back of the SUV,
What the [__] are we doing?
this is the cut that matters, the one
that tells the story and helps us
understand Alejandro's true character
and how his hatred has transformed him.
Don't forget about my daughter.
Taking into account his fixed eye line,
Fausto's reaction to his family being
ruthlessly slaughtered is also the only
thing Alejandro cares about. It's what
he came [music] for, and so that's what
Walker shows us. So he can get the
person that cut off his wife's head and
threw his daughter into a vat of acid.
Which makes this yet another example of
a cut that advances both the story and
the emotions driving [music] it.
Okay, we do see the aftermath of the
gunshots from this wide shot, but that
comes later because had we rapidly cut
between shots of Fausto's family being
killed, the spectacle of the violence
would have overshadowed the real point
of the scene, which isn't at all about
the violence. It's about the effect of
the violence and the character in
Alejandro that is revealed by it through
this reaction shot.
Walker's approach to cutting the
violence here, restrained as it is,
perfectly understands this. Holding for
as long as he does in the reaction
shots,
cutting to the wide for this moment.
This is thoughtful, emotion-based
cutting that very effectively helps us
see Alejandro as the singularly focused,
relentless force of nature that he is,
now consumed by vengeance and having
become something similar to the monster
he set out to destroy. I would like to
think that's why this final shot of
Alejandro finally completing his
vengeance features no cuts at all.
And even though it's impossible to
wholly separate his work from
Villeneuve's overall vision, Deakins'
exceptional work in capturing it and
everyone else that played a part in
creating Sicario, this is what Walker's
cutting does throughout the entire film.
Every cut,
or lack of a cut, every hold on the
result of a violent act, be it brief or
lengthy,
every reaction,
they're all intentional because they're
all story-driven, which, to quote the
great editor Walter Murch, is to say
that every cut is simultaneously true to
the emotion of the moment and advances
the story.
The amazing thing is that this is true
even during the film's most fleeting
moments of violence, which is a
testament to how Walker, through the
expertly juxtaposed rhythms of
unsettling violence and unflinching
violence, was able to construct these
moments in a way [music] that still
complements the narrative and reveals
character so effectively, and all while
maintaining the story's tension and
excitement.
It's fine, fine work that I wanted to
celebrate and try and draw some
attention to, even if it is 10 years
late.
Thank you very much for watching.